The next step in neutrophil function
will be destruction of the phagocytosed material.
Destruction of the phagocytosed material.
So the neutrophils will phagocytose, form a phagosome,
the phagosome will join with the lysosome,
and that's called the phagolysosome,
and then the phagolysosome will then be the area
in which the material that was consumed is destroyed.
So that's what we're talking about now,
destruction of phagocytosed material.
The destruction of phagocytosed material
can occur in two ways.
Remember that there is an oxygen-dependent mechanism,
which is actually the best mechanism of killing,
and then there is an oxygen-independent mechanism.
And so these are the two ways,
and as I've already said,
the oxygen-dependent mechanism
is actually the most effective way by which killing occurs.
Now, this requires a little bit of biochemistry
to understand this mechanism,
and because there's going to be a disease process,
that's important in this discussion,
I do need to review some of that biochemistry with you.
And I think the easiest way, again,
would be for me to simply just create a whiteboard
and explain this.
So the mechanism by which killing occurs
is going to be oxygen-dependent,
so we're going to obviously start with oxygen,
and one of the very first reactions that's going to occur
is that oxygen is going to be converted to superoxide.
All right, so superoxide.
And the enzyme that does this is NADPH oxidase.
So that's the first step.
NADPH oxidase will take oxygen and convert it to superoxide.
Very quickly, in an almost instantaneous reaction,
superoxide will be taken by superoxide dismutase,
which is an enzyme that we've already covered,
and superoxide dismutase will convert this superoxide
into hydrogen peroxide.
And then hydrogen peroxide will be grabbed by myeloperoxidase,
and will be, sorry, myeloperoxidase, MPO,
and will be converted to bleach,
which is basically HOCL.
So an HOCL is the key molecule
that is then going to destroy the organism.
This biochemistry is all high yield.
You have to know each and every one of these reactions,
and you need to understand
the step-by-step generation of this final product
because there are going to be diseases
that are going to apply to these different chemical reactions.
So with that as a background,
now let's go back and read together.
So an O2-dependent killing,
which is the most effective mechanism,
what's going to happen?
HOCL, i.e. bleach,
is going to be generated by the oxidative burst
in the phagolysosome,
and it's this HOCL that's going to play the key role
in destroying the phagocytosed microbe.
All right, next slide.
Now what's the mechanism?
I've already gone through this,
but let's read through it one more time.
So oxygen is converted to superoxide by NADPH oxidase.
That's also called the oxidative burst, by the way.
Superoxide is quickly converted to hydrogen peroxide
by superoxide dismutase,
and then hydrogen peroxide is converted to HOCL,
or bleach, by myeloperoxidase.
So all of these are high yield.
These enzymes are high yield, etc.
Now, that's the normal,
and there are a couple disease states
in which this normal can be disrupted.
And so the first of those
is called chronic granulomatous disease.
What happens in chronic granulomatous disease
is that you get poor O2-dependent killing.
Because O2-dependent killing is defective,
the patient then gets chronic granulomas
and gets regular infections and develops granulomas.
So that's called chronic granulomatous disease.
Now where is the defect?
The defect is due to NADPH oxidase.
Now this could be X-linked or autosomal recessive,
but the key problem is that there is an NADPH oxidase defect.
Now because there's an NADPH oxidase defect,
the patients are going to have problems generating bleach,
and because they have problems generating bleach,
they're going to get infections.
What's important here,
and we're not done yet
because there's a very important high yield principle,
is that the patients get infections
and they form granulomas with those infections.
But the key type of infection that they're going to get
are with organisms that are catalase positive.
And there's a list of five organisms
that are very high yield,
but I'm going to just tell you
what I think is the most high yield in a second.
But I just first want to discuss
this catalase positive idea
because it does show up on examinations as well.
So can we just go back
to a whiteboard for a minute,
and let me just go back to these reactions again.
So you remember that oxygen is going to form into superoxide,
and then superoxide is going to form into hydrogen peroxide,
and then hydrogen peroxide is eventually going to form into bleach, right?
And this was mediated by NADPH oxidase,
and this was mediated by myeloperoxidase.
Now, I just want to remind you that
when you think about this reaction,
what's really happening is that
we're eventually generating hydrogen peroxide,
and hydrogen peroxide is going to be converted to bleach.
There are really two ways
by which we can get hydrogen peroxide
to convert it to bleach.
One way would be to undergo this reaction
that I've drawn here,
where oxygen gets converted to superoxide,
and superoxide produces hydrogen peroxide,
and then this hydrogen peroxide becomes bleach.
And that requires NADPH oxidase.
Now, let's say that there's a patient
who is deficient in NADPH oxidase, right?
So this pathway is knocked out.
There actually is another way by which this bleach,
I'm sorry, by which this hydrogen peroxide
can be generated to form the bleach.
And that is that most bacteria
naturally produce a little bit of hydrogen peroxide.
So that for the vast majority of bacteria,
we could simply, if we're lacking NADPH oxidase,
we could simply take the hydrogen peroxide
from this bacteria,
grab the hydrogen peroxide from the bacteria,
and then produce bleach that way.
And so patients who have chronic granulomatous disease
really don't have a problem with most organisms
because most organisms are going to be able to,
are going to have bleach,
or sorry, have hydrogen peroxide,
and that hydrogen peroxide can be converted to bleach.
However, there are some bacteria that also produce catalase.
And catalase destroys hydrogen peroxide.
So that if a bacteria also produces catalase,
this pathway now gets knocked out.
And if this pathway gets knocked out,
and this pathway is also knocked out,
this can no longer be produced,
and therefore bleach can no longer be produced.
So that's why we only get infections
with catalase-positive bacteria
because it's with those catalase-positive bacteria
that we no longer have any source of hydrogen peroxide.
So I hope that's clear
because that is actually very high yield.
Now, in particular,
there are five organisms
that patients get infections with.
Staph aureus,
but everybody knows it,
and it's a very, very classic bug,
and it's not really the one
that shows up on examinations most often.
So staph aureus is a catalase-positive bug,
and it is a common bug that would arise
in a patient with chronic granulomatous disease.
But I would tell you,
in my own opinion,
more important is Pseudomonas sepaceae.
So Pseudomonas sepaceae
is actually another important bug
that is catalase-positive,
and that can also result in infections.
And because staph aureus is almost known
by every medical student,
examiners like to go after Pseudomonas sepaceae.
So do not forget Pseudomonas sepaceae
in the context of chronic granulomatous disease.
I hope that I made that clear.
But anyway, all this stuff is high yield,
and it's a lot of fun
because we get to tie in biochemistry
and microbiology with pathology,
and that's really what medicine is all about.
The next important principle
concerning chronic granulomatous disease
is something called the nitro-blue tetrazoleum test,
i.e. the NBT test.
Now this is a test that's used
to screen for chronic granulomatous disease,
and what it does is it asks the question,
this test asks the question,
do we have the ability
to convert oxygen to superoxide?
If oxygen can be converted to superoxide,
the superoxide will actually convert,
will actually change the NBT,
or this nitro-blue tetrazoleum, to blue.
So why don't I make this super clear for you
by drawing it in a picture.
Again, you start with oxygen,
and the oxygen gets converted to superoxide,
as we've already stated,
and then the superoxide gets converted
to hydrogen peroxide,
and the hydrogen peroxide gets converted
to HOCl, right?
Now, what does the nitro-blue tetrazoleum test ask?
It asks the question,
is this reaction intact?
And if this reaction is intact,
if you introduce the nitro-blue tetrazoleum
into the test tube with the neutrophils,
this will then turn blue.
Okay?
If the reaction is intact,
the dye will turn blue.
So if the reaction is not intact,
the dye will actually remain colorless, right?
And so patients who have chronic granulomatous disease
are not able to produce this reaction,
and therefore they will not be able to change the dye
to its blue color,
and the dye will remain colorless.
So that's an important test to be familiar with.
Now, there is another disease
that can also affect this pathway,
and that is the fact that MPO converts,
remember that MPO converts hydrogen peroxide to HOCl.
MPO can be defective as well.
And if MPO is defective,
that's called an MPO deficiency.
And again, patients will not be able to produce bleach.
So in MPO or myeloperoxidase deficiency,
the interesting thing is that the vast majority of patients
are actually asymptomatic.
So in real life,
if you were to ever see such a patient,
which is very rare,
but if you were to ever see such a patient,
they would be asymptomatic most likely.
However, on examinations,
they get an increased risk for candida infections.
And I guess in real life as well,
if they're ever going to have symptoms,
it's going to be candida infections,
although usually these patients don't have symptoms.
But on board exams,
they usually have an increased risk for candida infections.
I'm going to talk about this in a slide in a minute.
However, what I want to highlight here,
since I took all the pain to draw this picture,
is that the NBT test will be normal.
Because in these patients,
in myeloperoxidase deficiency,
this reaction is fine.
The problem is this reaction down here.
So the NBT test will turn blue,
but the patients will be lacking myeloperoxidase instead.
Okay, so with that,
let's actually talk briefly about this slide,
which is the next slide,
which is the MPO deficiency.
So MPO deficiency results in what?
It's a defective conversion of H2O2 to HOCL.
I've already explained that to you.
And most patients are asymptomatic.
However, if there ever is a problem,
the problem is usually an increased risk
for candida infections.
And high-yield NBT test is normal.
So it is important to be familiar
with myeloperoxidase deficiency.
Now let's go forward.
The second way by which neutrophils can kill
is called O2-independent killing.
It's less effective,
and it occurs via enzymes
that are present within the leukocyte,
usually within the secondary granules of the leukocyte.
So for example,
lysozyme is an enzyme
that's useful for destroying microbes.
Major basic protein.
This is major basic protein here.
It is an enzyme present in eosinophils,
which is useful for destroying microbes as well.
And this is a little less effective
than oxygen-dependent killing.
The final stage of neutrophil arrival
is called resolution.
So once the infection is destroyed,
within 24 hours,
the neutrophils will disappear.
Now, it's important for you to know
for examinations,
they like you to know
how neutrophils disappear.
And what happens is
the neutrophils die within the tissue,
and they die via apoptosis.
So all neutrophils,
once they get into tissue,
will die within the tissue,
and they'll die via apoptosis.
And recall that pus
is basically dead neutrophils within fluid.
And that's sort of the final resolution,
which is you have to know
that it's very high yield.
Neutrophils undergo apoptosis,
and that's the way by which
they resolve themselves within the tissue.
Now, once the neutrophils
are sort of done their job,
the next phase will be
to bring in the macrophages.
Can you remember I told you
that there were three phases
of acute inflammation?
There's a fluid phase,
which occurs immediately.
There's a neutrophil phase,
which peaks at 24 hours
or a day into inflammation.
And then there's a final phase,
and that final phase
is the macrophage phase.
And so this is now
what we want to briefly touch on,
the macrophage phase.
And so the macrophages peak
two to three days
after inflammation begins.
They occur after the neutrophils arrive,
and they're derived
from monocytes in the blood.
So you've got these monocytes
floating around in the blood,
and it's the monocytes
that eventually get into tissue,
and when they get into tissue,
we call them macrophages.
Now, we should just be thankful
that the macrophages,
i.e. the monocytes,
they come into the tissue
the exact same way
that the neutrophils do.
So they use margination,
they use rolling,
they use adhesion,
they use transmigration.
So guess what?
That makes their life really easy,
because now we don't have to repeat
all of these steps.
We're already familiar with them.
Once the macrophages
get into the tissue,
they actually ingest
via phagocytosis,
and then they destroy
the phagocytosed material
using enzymes
in the secondary granules.
For the most part,
neutrophil, sorry,
for the most part,
macrophages don't really do
a lot of oxygen-dependent killing.
Their primary mechanism
is oxygen-independent
using enzymes
in the secondary granules,
and I would say
one of the key enzymes
is lysozyme.
So we should be familiar
with the fact
that lysozyme
in the secondary granules
are very useful
for the macrophages
to destroy phagocytosed material
or to kill off
phagocytosed material.
The final point
to close off this section
is that the macrophages,
in my mind,
sort of the way
I think about macrophages
is that they are managers.
They then manage
the next step
of the acute inflammatory process.
And so when the macrophages
come in,
they sort of look around
their managers
and they say,
hmm, has a good job been done?
Does something more
need to be done?
Do we need to call
in somebody else?
So if they come
into the tissue
and they see that,
well, excellent job,
the neutrophils
have really killed off everything
and it's now time
to begin the next step,
they will then induce
resolution and healing.
So they'll still
kind of look around
and say,
hmm, okay,
these bugs are dead,
these bugs are dead.
Neutrophils did a great job.
Let's call in healing
because it's now time
to fix the tissue.
And the way by which
they do that
is partially by secreting
IL-10 and TGF-beta.
Now the key thing
about IL-10 and TGF-beta,
these are both things
that shut down
the inflammatory process.
So I think it's important
to remember
that IL-10 and TGF-beta,
they're kind of
anti-inflammatory.
They sort of shut down
the inflammatory process
and then they also allow
for the eventual
calling in of healing.
And we're going to talk
about wound healing
a little later
in this chapter.
Another possibility
is that the neutrophils
can come in
and they could say,
uh-oh,
we've got to do
a lot more work.
They may come in
two to three days later
and say,
neutrophils look like
they need some help.
So they can actually
call in additional neutrophils
allowing for acute,
continued acute inflammation.
A couple important points here
which become
is the mechanism
by which the neutrophils
call in,
sorry,
is the mechanism
by which the macrophages
call in the neutrophils.
Again,
I'm going to repeat this
because it's high yield.
IL-8
is the cytokine
produced by macrophages
that call in the neutrophil.
Now when additional neutrophils
are called in,
that's going to result
in continued acute inflammation.
So although we call it
acute inflammation
and although it peaks
at one day,
acute inflammation
is not defined by time,
it's defined by the response.
So for example,
a patient could undergo
acute inflammation
and have acute inflammation
for six weeks
and that's because
the macrophages
keep secreting IL-8
which calls in
more and more neutrophils.
So the hallmarks
of neutrophilic inflammation,
particularly the formation
of pus,
tells you that there is
a continued acute
inflammatory response.
So please be aware of that
because sometimes examiners
like to confuse you
by saying that there is
a process that's been going on
for eight weeks
but the patient's still
coughing up pus
and so what is actually
happening
and the notion here
is that it is still
an example of acute inflammation
even if it's eight weeks
into the infection
because of the fact
that you still have
a neutrophilic response
and neutrophils
are what define
acute inflammation.
Now another possibility
is that the macrophages
can come in
and they could basically
sense that
the organism
is a particular type
of organism
that needs to be walled off
to protect the rest
of the host,
the organ
and so they can
actually result in
they can actually
call in
or create an abscess
and what's an abscess?
An abscess
is an area of fibrosis
so let's pretend
that this is an organ
sorry
this is an organ
and so what the macrophages
can do
is they can create
a wall of fibrosis
around the area
of infection
and so that
the inflammation
sort of gets trapped
within this
within this space
and that would be
called an abscess
and abscess
is basically
a walled off area
of acute inflammation
and the neutrophils
are really the ones
that manage
the formation
of an abscess
and they would form
an abscess
in response
to very particular
organisms
as you're well aware of
and then finally
the last thing
that the neutrophils
could do
they could come in
and they could say
uh oh
looks like the neutrophils
aren't able to handle this
for example
this is virus
and the virus
is not well handled
by the neutrophils
and so the macrophages
could call in
chronic inflammation
they ingest
some of the antigen
and the microbes
and then they express it
on their
MHC class 2
because they're
antigen presenting cells
and it's the expression
of those particles
in MHC class 2
that could eventually
result in
the activation
via helper T cells
of chronic inflammation
and so again
macrophages
are managers
of the acute
inflammatory process
and they can then
dictate what's going
to happen next
and so with that
we actually want to
we're going to be here
concluding
acute inflammation
and our next section
is going to be
chronic inflammation
but let's stop here
and give you a chance
to take a little bit
of a breather
easier
so
and so
it's going to be here
and this is actually
nice
and it's going to be
friendly
setup
so
we're going to be
for o'err
now
and so
we're going to be
reflecting on
oxy
and so
we're going to be
connected
to them
nous
and so
we're going to be
noch
on the next section
with warranty
of course
and so
let's just
we're going to be
vedенной
later
so
we're going to
we're going to be
another
and we're done